<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encomiasticke elogies. Written by Augustine Taylor</title>
            <author>Taylor, Augustine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13411</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857008</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857008</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22667</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13411)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22667)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1118:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Encomiasticke elogies. Written by Augustine Taylor</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Augustine.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:1"/>
            <p>ENCOMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ASTICKE <hi>Elogies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by AVGVSTINE TAYLOR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes.</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <l>LEt me intreate (where e're theſe come by chance)</l>
            <l>Them ſilent, whom's betray'd by Ignorance.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>HIS BOOKE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Handfull I preſent: no more becauſe</l>
               <l>Such reuerence, ſerues my Patrons: Order draws</l>
               <l>Theſe labours, in theſe limites: Being firſt,</l>
               <l>My actions forme's a ſtranger; and vnnurſt</l>
               <l>By whether cenſure ſhould, or good, or ill;</l>
               <l>Doubting (how e're 'tis needfull) that my skill</l>
               <l>Produces in this kind. Suffice the frame</l>
               <l>Keepes concord in the time, More doth remaine</l>
               <l>My ſtore ſhall after publiſh: But ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>A diſcord; Then this little I diſcloſe</l>
               <l>Is more, too much: then if it were the beſt,</l>
               <l>Too little: onely for becauſe doth reſt</l>
               <l>To lawfull heights, a ſtaire. When no amends</l>
               <l>Can ſcape a fall, where rude neglect aſcends.</l>
               <l>I ſee times errours, and dares not accord</l>
               <l>To wade by Star-light where the Tyde and Ford</l>
               <l>Are ſtrangers to mee: Venturing when the Sunne</l>
               <l>Daignes to diſcouer paſſage, then what's done</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:22667:3"/>
               <l>May ſee to do in th'action, I'le refraine</l>
               <l>After he, takes a cloud-maske, ſeemes to blame</l>
               <l>My entrance. This comes to the beſt of men</l>
               <l>To borrow true light. Neuer ſhall my pen</l>
               <l>Proceede without commiſſion; and obſcur'd</l>
               <l>Vnder not couering wings: I am aſſur'd</l>
               <l>That I expect, there, is not. If to whom</l>
               <l>My budding labours go; be turn'd. At home</l>
               <l>I not reſerue my after times, to ſpend</l>
               <l>But forraging, mourne diſability. Lend</l>
               <l>Beſt able, here ſome grace. Cenſure my rime</l>
               <l>To the vnripeneſſe of my thriuing time,</l>
               <l>That grant; and proue my merite how it muſt;</l>
               <l>I muſt, and would embrace it: and 'tis iuſt.</l>
               <l>Your names, ſpeakes your owne worthes. How ere I'm made.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By his chiefe ſeruant loue may be betrai'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:3"/>Encomiaſticke Elogies.</head>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 1. <hi>TO BRITAINE.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>T'Admire theſe appoſitions when them ſtand</l>
               <l>By are iudicious; not to vnderſtand</l>
               <l>Will force thy wonder cenſur'd. Properly ſtand</l>
               <l>Who ere would greet a King, ſhould with his Land</l>
               <l>Proclaime's acquaintance. Britaine I may ſing</l>
               <l>The faireſt Land rul'd by the worthieſt King;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Altiſſimè: ſuper-Ela.</hi> Neareſt dumbe</l>
               <l>Speake of thy praiſers praiſe; not ſing't but hum</l>
               <l>T'aland ſo worth, vnequal'd: ſhould my Muſe</l>
               <l>(Charg'd with loues-duties-zeale,) the ſpeech refuſe</l>
               <l>The land and nature ownes? and others vſe?</l>
               <l>That were to publiſh. But them cannot chuſe</l>
               <l>Speakes Engliſh. This contempt to ſtrangers knowne:</l>
               <l>They'l find iuſt cauſe to diſeſteeme our owne</l>
               <l>After wee catch at theirs. Who did digreſſe</l>
               <l>Grecian? or Romane? <hi>Homers</hi> worthineſſe</l>
               <l>Got wing in Greece, he did not's country ſcorne.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Virgil;</hi> all grant famous'd firſt, and borne</l>
               <l>In Mantua. Britaine, we may be bold</l>
               <l>To ſpeake thee well as Greeke, or Romane could,</l>
               <l>Speake Greece, or Rome. And if bee loſt, thy part</l>
               <l>Of glory: The defect comes to our Art</l>
               <l>And claimes th'originall. O I ſpye the cauſe,</l>
               <l>Defection 'tis, that th'imperfection drawes</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:22667:4"/>
               <l>To be our ſhare: This time amend might bring,</l>
               <l>To make them leaue to hum, that cannot ſing.</l>
               <l>Silence to diſcord; worthy'ſt Sonneting</l>
               <l>Might entertaine her valew: length her wing.</l>
               <l>Our language giues, as beſt: 'tis <hi>Sidneyes</hi> friend,</l>
               <l>And he its more: Sweet'ſt <hi>Daniell</hi> (as vnkend)</l>
               <l>My better deere reſpect, reſpects. There bee</l>
               <l>Praiſe-worthy others: But great'ſt throng I ſee</l>
               <l>Nor ſence, nor accent holds. Thus Poeſie's ſlaine!</l>
               <l>Hee that thinkes to be heard, muſt ſtrip the ſtraine</l>
               <l>Of the time iangling diſcords: beſt, complaine</l>
               <l>And pitty; <hi>Abell,</hi> to be kil'd by <hi>Caine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To build yet, glory; and make Brittaine ſtand,</l>
               <l>Is t'make our Language famous: So's our land:</l>
               <l>Since our beſt, King; beſt Muſes fauours, thus.</l>
               <l>Shal's change a <hi>melior,</hi> to an <hi>optimus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 2. Conſecrated to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt <hi>of men,</hi> IAMES <hi>by the</hi> Grace of God, King of Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France, and Ireland, &amp;c. Trueſt Defendor of the <hi>Trueſt Faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>COmmemorable moſt, by ſuch that can</l>
            <l>With true faire courſe, know how to lift a man</l>
            <l>Aboue the men: Who can ſo, may relate;</l>
            <l>Thy vertues further do precede thy State</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:4"/>
            <l>In glory; then thy ſtate is ſeene excell</l>
            <l>Degree of low'ſt compare: And aptly well</l>
            <l>Excited to expreſſe a ſhare in which</l>
            <l>A poore m'acquire acceptance as a rich:</l>
            <l>So, th'action brings. To thee I ioy to ſing:</l>
            <l>My Iudge is Europes, (Poets) chiefeſt King.</l>
            <l>EN BRITANNIA.</l>
            <l>Behold a ſtranger ſight, nor ſtrange becauſe</l>
            <l>Expected, and deſir'd; 'tis action drawes</l>
            <l>The admiration on's: When for a flight</l>
            <l>To ſee, we ſtor'd our Turrets: then not might</l>
            <l>Preiudicate the forme: 'Gaine; tops be ſtoring;</l>
            <l>(You ſaw the iourneing) but to note the ſoaring</l>
            <l>Of a moſt Princely Bird: When from the North</l>
            <l>Of Albion, did Princely enter forth</l>
            <l>An Eagle, and along by's Lordly ſide,</l>
            <l>Accompanied, the faireſt, worthieſt Bride</l>
            <l>As could her Sexe preferre; And next to them</l>
            <l>Came the next worthieſt, of that royall Stem.</l>
            <l>This Princely Worthies Leader, onward came</l>
            <l>Imperiouſly: Whoſe Style and happy Name,</l>
            <l>Fame's Trumpets notic'd. Glad (for that he is,)</l>
            <l>Conceiue him comne: Not heare from Tueſis</l>
            <l>His progreſſe needs conſcrib'de. For how ere ſo</l>
            <l>My Horology could, it may not ſhow</l>
            <l>To them Teſtators: that they better know.</l>
            <l>To Thames, there holds his courſe; Th'Eagles on wing,</l>
            <l>Not highly ſpher'd ſince comne: He was the King</l>
            <l>Of all his kind, and richeſt in renowne,</l>
            <l>Before the time gaue to him Englands Crowne;</l>
            <l>'Twas Englands cuſtome that her crown'd ſtill King'd</l>
            <l>Th'vnking'd, before receiuer; he hath bring'd</l>
            <l>Another Crowne to hers. A fruitfull Queene.</l>
            <l>Made's happy with an Aciry to keep greene,</l>
            <l>Our (when change) dying court; ſo erſt, <hi>ſed non</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The time ſhewes grants, a bleſſed vnion</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:5"/>
            <l>To command forraigne good; by him is ioyn'd</l>
            <l>Our ioyes to Guard. Nor ſtamp nor impreſſe coin'd</l>
            <l>By powerfull'ſt foe, can iniure's, &amp;c.</l>
            <l>Wee ſerue the beſt example; peace hath done</l>
            <l>Britaine more grace, then euer ſword. And wonne,</l>
            <l>And weares more: and th'old freedome. Such a Bird</l>
            <l>Our Eagle's knowne, the low'ſt voice is heard</l>
            <l>That humbly craues admittance; and reſpected:</l>
            <l>He ſoares not ſo paſt call, as ſees neglected</l>
            <l>Oppreſſion. Neither low but that his height,</l>
            <l>Sees vertue truely honour'd, with her weight</l>
            <l>In all that's to aduance her. Keepes a hould,</l>
            <l>Nor high, nor low: but as an Eagle ſhould</l>
            <l>Obſerue, to be obſeru'd. This matchleſſe obiect</l>
            <l>Approues himſelfe true King, and loyall Subiect.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Subiect to vertues, to all ills, oppreſſor.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>All Rights maintainer, and all wrongs redreſſor.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He's beſt. Thinke him (then I ſpeake) better, &amp;c.</l>
            <l>More knowes this, then knowes thee: It can be found</l>
            <l>That is not heare, but for't ſo true a ground</l>
            <l>As truth. And being ſo, this little frame</l>
            <l>Comes ſingularly but to attend thy name,</l>
            <l>For large ones, liue thy vertues.</l>
            <l>To thy moſt ſacred Maieſty, comes thus</l>
            <l>Conioyned loue and duty: not <hi>ſolus</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Appeare can either: from a new riſe Muſe,</l>
            <l>Of yeares ſcarce twenties-teller: Not in vſe</l>
            <l>With the times ſtraine ſo earely. For this firſt,</l>
            <l>Great Maieſty daigne grace. What if the worſt,</l>
            <l>Becauſe then borne? Yet after ſhall my ſwan</l>
            <l>Proue; Britaines Soueraigne is aboue a man.</l>
            <l>Immortall, more then humane. Time ſhall ſing,</l>
            <l>Of but one King; 'boue <hi>Iames,</hi> Great Britaines King.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>In altiſſimo Coelo. </hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties humble, and true-faithfull Subiect.</hi> Auguſtine Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:5"/>
            <head>ENCOM. 3. To the great and hopefull CHARLES, Prince of Great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and Ireland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>TOp-ſpring of Britaines hope, as to the Sphere,</l>
            <l>Whence deareſt expectation waits, to heare</l>
            <l>The voice of her content. To thee I meane,</l>
            <l>That on the ſluce of Englands Hippocreane</l>
            <l>Aſcends in good, to grace the land, and ſtreame.</l>
            <l>More do admire, then vnderſtand the ſtate</l>
            <l>Of vertues thine; could them admire, relate</l>
            <l>Thy Princely true proportion in all parts:</l>
            <l>'Twould vrge thoſe can but meaneſt part of Arts</l>
            <l>Aduancement; offer ſuch true notes to thee,</l>
            <l>Would force admir'd, thy good, their loyalty,</l>
            <l>Through euery knowing clime; that vnderſtands</l>
            <l>What Prince, and Subiect meanes. To all thoſe lands</l>
            <l>That whilome cal'd Rome Miſtreſſe; <hi>Caeſars</hi> to</l>
            <l>Stood ſeruants-like, vncapt, I giue to kno:</l>
            <l>Romes Triumphes can but boaſt, t'haue beene times preter</l>
            <l>Britaines but late begunne, therefore times detter.</l>
            <l>Our Thames (then) Tyber equals. Our Swans be</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:6"/>
            <l>Knowne publicke ſprung from ſo great Royalty</l>
            <l>As then was hers. The difference can but this,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Such was on Tyber; is on Thameſis.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Not Europe-ruling-<hi>Caeſars,</hi> thus had liu'd</l>
            <l>Famous'd by infants breath; had they not giu'd</l>
            <l>A life to Poeſie: Faireſt Tombes will breake,</l>
            <l>Ruſt, and conſume; not Poeſie whilſt any ſpeake,</l>
            <l>Of any Language ſpoken. Know great Prince</l>
            <l>The wortrthi'ſt ornaments that Princes, ſince</l>
            <l>They tooke the name, was left, and onely fram'd</l>
            <l>By Poeſie: and is. Who is there nam'd</l>
            <l>That's well accounted worthy, would not vſe</l>
            <l>Before a dead ſeene picture, what a Muſe</l>
            <l>(Well able) can produce? <hi>Neſciunt.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Th'one a ſhort time endures, and honours neuer</l>
            <l>Them it preſents: Th'other continues euer</l>
            <l>Whil'ſt vertue's good: and honours. Being men,</l>
            <l>The beſt of Natures fabricke: Why ſhould then</l>
            <l>Pictures be thought ſo worth? as if he dy'd</l>
            <l>That did not leaue his equall. If not try'd</l>
            <l>To be in ſubſtance; yet in ſhew 'tis knowne:</l>
            <l>Hee ne're was knowne depart, that like his owne</l>
            <l>Left no proportion: For ſome worth (indeed)</l>
            <l>Death leaues not life example, I do heed</l>
            <l>By accidents. Then, ſuch parts to expreſſe</l>
            <l>Nature and Art, confirmes tru'ſt tutereſſe</l>
            <l>From Poeſie. All worth and euery action</l>
            <l>Re-acts in noting thoughts; thence. Yet giue faction</l>
            <l>Of painting euen courſe: but grant it ſo</l>
            <l>That Poeſie ſtand to publiſh: Euery ſhowe</l>
            <l>Being ſubſtanc'd, better's honour'd, vertue's like</l>
            <l>To liue thy age, in thee: Then be to ſeeke</l>
            <l>New ſhelter, leaue her not: ſtill in thy name</l>
            <l>Thy worth, and ſhee ſhall ſhare great'ſt pars of fame.</l>
            <l>In Arts and Vertues ripe; thy actions ſhow</l>
            <l>Now when thy yeares but greene: All hope to know</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:6"/>
            <l>Both mature; both exceed. Now <hi>Melior eſt,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Altior, aſcendens:</hi> Thriuing to the beſt;</l>
            <l>And thought fame, breath to lend. This harmony</l>
            <l>(Plaid by an actiue Muſe) doth wait to ſee</l>
            <l>From thee repaire; and from thee fetch a ſtraine</l>
            <l>For a tenth worthy; Englands <hi>Charlemaigne.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Th'art in the faireſt path, for rule beſt Rules,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>When Princes Courts turne Academicke ſchooles.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Proceed great Prince, and ſhall thy time, thy ſeed,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Summon beſt Trumpets at fames lips, to bleed.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe obſeruant, <hi>AVGVSTINE TAYLOR.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 4. To ANNE, the ſacred Queene of Great Brittaine, &amp;c. Her moſt <hi>excellent Maieſty.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>NOt lou'd <hi>Pandora,</hi> when her <hi>Theſſaly</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Perſwaded; not a Queene ſo worth as ſhee,</l>
            <l>The world did, nor could nurſe. <hi>Deucalion</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To ſee his mother; glory'd. Study'd on</l>
            <l>Her ſeuerall gifts, alow'd: and did perſwade,</l>
            <l>So true perfection Nature er'ſt not made,</l>
            <l>Nor after would: and ſhe was cauſe alone,</l>
            <l>That ſome haue little beauty, and ſome none.</l>
            <l>The chiefe of natures ſtore, <hi>Deucalion</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Sufficed was his mould. Great Britaines <hi>Anne</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:7"/>
            <l>Is better worth to King, State, Land, and mee:</l>
            <l>Then e'rſt <hi>Pandora</hi> was to <hi>Theſſalie.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Vertues were there, but better now is here</l>
            <l>Men now are more iudicious, then they were</l>
            <l>Then: and more this confirmes? Nature no more</l>
            <l>Expects thought can demand; then's in the ſtore</l>
            <l>Of the impreſſe ſhee gaue thee. Art to that</l>
            <l>Conioines ſuch right, as knowledge wonders at:</l>
            <l>And may become a Queene. Not that I know,</l>
            <l>Can giue leaſt grace to woman, but to ſhow</l>
            <l>This vertues Patroneſſe can. But by thy worth</l>
            <l>Ne're in thy ſex. My thoughts had noted forth</l>
            <l>The difference what might be. In that doth ſhine</l>
            <l>Matter immortall, greater part diuine.</l>
            <l>To ſpeake thy eu'ry worth is more to do</l>
            <l>Till (number'd ſome) I thought on. Comming to</l>
            <l>A curious frame, to ſee it all that come</l>
            <l>Their ſights hold it like deare: but when to ſome</l>
            <l>The worth and how 'tis done, the Architect</l>
            <l>A ſtranger comes to view; 'tis ſ'indirect</l>
            <l>To cenſure, yet right famous: He will tell</l>
            <l>He muſt haue time to note it, it ſeemes well.</l>
            <l>The more he ſpeakes it betters't: grants it ſuch</l>
            <l>As he not knew, neither can praiſe ſo much</l>
            <l>As it deſerues. But then to grace the deed,</l>
            <l>And end his taske, he ſweares it doth exceed.</l>
            <l>I leaue thee ſo imperfect; 'tis ſo when</l>
            <l>One man has made a worke that n'other men</l>
            <l>Nor vnderſtands, nor frames: T'admire is all</l>
            <l>The vnconceiuing can; and ſo I ſhall</l>
            <l>As ſuch, my charge effect: and nearer breake,</l>
            <l>They do admire and's dumbe, I'dmire and ſpeake</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pandora's</hi> ſuper-equal'd. <hi>Pallas</hi> gaue</l>
            <l>Not ſo much wiſedome as th'art ſeene to haue:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Venus</hi> not ſo much beauty. And for skill</l>
            <l>In heauenly numbers not <hi>Apollo</hi> will</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:7"/>
            <l>Diſcloſe hee better grac'd her. <hi>Mercury</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For breath-ſweete numbers the like ſtraine to thee,</l>
            <l>To her allow'd not. Theſe were all her ſtore:</l>
            <l>Theſe all be thine, and better. Others more:</l>
            <l>Chaſtity, euery vertue. Thou art knowne</l>
            <l>Paſt her in number: paſt her in her owne.</l>
            <l>Paſt my compariſon. Time thy Stile ſhall bring;</l>
            <l>The Daughter, Siſter, Wife vnto a King:</l>
            <l>And mother in future. Thou art onely Queene</l>
            <l>Of ſpacious Brittaine; where two late hath beene,</l>
            <l>And where not long ſince many. Long remaine</l>
            <l>Bleſt mother; to another, <hi>Charlemaigne.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And I ſhall liue to ſee the thame inioy</l>
            <l>Another <hi>Illion</hi> in another Troy.</l>
            <l>So Noble ſpirits ſet her breaſt vpon</l>
            <l>As were the grand ſonnes of <hi>Laomedon,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And much more happy.</l>
            <l>There ſhall thou be recorded by the Muſes</l>
            <l>So long as Thame keepes her oppoſed ſluces</l>
            <l>From kiſſing either other.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Educere vtinam potuero! </hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties freely deuoted ſeruant. <hi>AVGVSTINE TAYLOR.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 5. TO TIME.</head>
            <l>SVbiections nurſe; nor ſubiect but t'attend</l>
            <l>The Soule. The courſe of thee to apprehend.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:8"/>
            <l>Not to our part belongs: nor that's my aime.</l>
            <l>Time paſt leaues what hee was, nor I to gaine</l>
            <l>What part's to come, affect; nor ſhould: but that</l>
            <l>A ſafety thence deriu'd. I wiſh but at</l>
            <l>The preſent to conioine: ſuffice I do.</l>
            <l>How that's ſpent paſt, them paſt haue witneſſ'd ſo</l>
            <l>I do retaine ſome formes. How now it is</l>
            <l>Moſt ſee, but few can cenſure: Some ſay this,</l>
            <l>Age, as the worſt is knowne: This may be ſcan'd,</l>
            <l>Diſpraiſe ſits hud-wink'd; Some may meane this land</l>
            <l>That diſcommends another. All lands ill:</l>
            <l>I ſpeake to flattery ignorant; But will</l>
            <l>My ſpeech (for that) b'alow'd? I know it may.</l>
            <l>He that can free it, reels not in the ſway;</l>
            <l>Of them, that's now vnweldy. He's aboue</l>
            <l>In ſtrength, as in his vertues: Thoſe that moue</l>
            <l>Spher'd in the baſeſt element; and keepe</l>
            <l>No duties to good frame: The time doth weepe;</l>
            <l>(From them) to take the wrongs. And can expreſſe</l>
            <l>Our land the beſt; and worſt: beſt, to poſſeſſe</l>
            <l>Such treaſures, ſuch a King; and worſt, becauſe,</l>
            <l>Not theſe ſuperiours, the poſſeſſours drawes</l>
            <l>To gratefulneſſe; and change: A change is ment</l>
            <l>From the abuſes ripe. More doth exempt</l>
            <l>Our actions heere, bad acted; From the hope</l>
            <l>Of abſolutions, then theres in no ſcope</l>
            <l>Of gouernment. Wee haue examples tell</l>
            <l>In that we do; in that we do not well.</l>
            <l>And what's well done's diſtinguiſh'd: And with thoſe</l>
            <l>That good intreates, good actions may repoſe</l>
            <l>And th'Authour ſtrength'd to do. We cannot ſay</l>
            <l>Wee know not what's to do, for wee betray</l>
            <l>Our ſelues that to alledge: The truth is ſo,</l>
            <l>(I know wee may) I know we will not know.</l>
            <l>To right belong the charge! but ſtay; I ſaid</l>
            <l>To ſee the forme of times Encomion made.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:8"/>
            <l>And ſhall; his wrongs, deſcrib'd; aſſiſt the part</l>
            <l>I promis'd. Nor Ile runne int' a deſert</l>
            <l>Confuſedly, of all his wrongs to ſay,</l>
            <l>I make my charge, but part: to giue a way</l>
            <l>Of vnderſtanding t'all. Hee is ſo cleere</l>
            <l>As innocence: His ſubiects do appeare</l>
            <l>Many deform'd, in manners; not in ſhape:</l>
            <l>Whence growes this ſtrange effect? Another rape</l>
            <l>Muſt time in ſable plaine, and 'gaine before</l>
            <l>Th' offendor ſee th'offence? muſt all our ſtore</l>
            <l>Admitted for our good, dure this neglect?</l>
            <l>Sad deſolation ſhall againe effect</l>
            <l>Confuſions end? More chaos preſent like,</l>
            <l>The more my thoughts attend: it ſeemes to ſtrike</l>
            <l>I feare when not expected. What's the vſe</l>
            <l>(Vnmannerly) ſhould theſe effects produce?</l>
            <l>Ambition. All miſtruſt confirmes the ſame</l>
            <l>For primate agent. Ill! behold the frame</l>
            <l>Of times-diſorder-breeder: firſt a man</l>
            <l>Grounds my deſcription: do's attire but ſcan</l>
            <l>In ſubſtance, as in ſhow. Wee haue of thoſe</l>
            <l>Whence as the vulgar deemes; moſt ſtrangely groes</l>
            <l>A more then mortall ſtate. Nor this effect</l>
            <l>Makes this, thus cenſur'd for any reſpect</l>
            <l>Of inn, but outward ſhow. Poore ignorance</l>
            <l>(Decay'd in ſelfe, and cenſure.) In a trance</l>
            <l>Stands, painting, idolizing. It is ſo</l>
            <l>Subſtance liues (much) vncenſur'd: men not know</l>
            <l>Its being in this Maske. My ſelfe haue beene</l>
            <l>I'th' neighboring lodge to Gallants; with them, ſeene,</l>
            <l>I ſhall not boaſt to ſay: Nor I agree,</l>
            <l>Nor glories, that ſuch ſhould be ſeene, with mee:</l>
            <l>Yet thus much I conceiu'd; ſome are within</l>
            <l>Deafe, as vnfurniſht wainſcoate; and begin</l>
            <l>A ſerious Diſcourſe, fals in a trance</l>
            <l>The all they can is pace, and countenance:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:9"/>
            <l>And but, by ſeaſons, them, and yet be theſe</l>
            <l>Attir'd as the not-knowing a diſeaſe</l>
            <l>Of humane courſe. Here; if all them attends,</l>
            <l>Attain'd conſtruction. Noting, well the ends</l>
            <l>Thy would be harſhe, as tedious. That ambition</l>
            <l>Theſe times wins thus, aduancement: the permiſſion</l>
            <l>Giues not ſ'vnciuill freedome. 'Tis admir'd</l>
            <l>Ambition t'enter where nothing's acquir'd</l>
            <l>To glory in. Admit the beſt that can;</l>
            <l>Or birth, or fate, attributed to man:</l>
            <l>And he to whom 'tis lent, diſcretly know,</l>
            <l>(And vſe) humility; hee obſerueth ſo</l>
            <l>But as he ſhould. And this I haue diſcern'd</l>
            <l>Out of the time, in worthineſſe beſt learn'd</l>
            <l>Who euer bee: makes not his habite ſuch</l>
            <l>As can betray his worth, hee doubts ſo much</l>
            <l>His owne debility. I do euer note</l>
            <l>Them inly poore ſeeke honour by their coate</l>
            <l>To purchaſe. But all the conceiuing will</l>
            <l>Conceiue how things are done; and to them, ill;</l>
            <l>Reſerue a penſion fit. Proud ignorance</l>
            <l>May paſſe, paſt all the vulgar; and aduance</l>
            <l>Her forme 'boue their conceite: but (ſurely) ſhall</l>
            <l>By th'able bee diſtinguiſh'd; and then fall</l>
            <l>From the improper height, to one more true:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Merite muſt inioy right, vnright haue due.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Our Rector, <hi>rectè</hi> grants. Longer to runne</l>
            <l>In Meeter on theſe Oddes, procures not done</l>
            <l>The part that's vndone. Th'enemy to time</l>
            <l>Ambition's prou'd; a monſter, cannot clime</l>
            <l>T'her height alone; but by all ills aſcend:</l>
            <l>To other ſinnes, ſinnes want: but doe contend</l>
            <l>In her together, which ſhall ſtuffe the chaire</l>
            <l>Exceſſe is crown'd in. Time, now to declare</l>
            <l>His wrongs and not be tedious; ſpeakes ambition,</l>
            <l>In whom the reſt are nurs'd; with this petition</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:9"/>
            <l>Intreates amends: That ſhee may looſe her foote.</l>
            <l>The branches cannot wither, whil'ſt the roote</l>
            <l>So largely can command. This ruining crime</l>
            <l>'Has men betray'd: and now's betraying time.</l>
            <l>But I haue much digreſſ'd: I vow'd to time</l>
            <l>An <hi>Apotheoſis,</hi> in panygiricke line.</l>
            <l>And may what's ſaid obſerue: What's ſaid's obſeru'd</l>
            <l>In prouing him iniur'd. A time's reſeru'd</l>
            <l>To Authoriz'd due caſtigations on</l>
            <l>Them euer time abus'd. How ere vpon</l>
            <l>His courſe we do complaine: Right vnderſtood;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Subiects, offend moſt where their King is good.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Them t'ill inclin'd. A good and vertuous King</l>
            <l>Deſires; expects a change; and lothes ro bring</l>
            <l>Confuſion to the vnreform'd. Is not</l>
            <l>That pilgrime to b'vnpitty'd, that forgot</l>
            <l>The path he preſent trode. And like a child</l>
            <l>When't feeds th'affection; and's drawne on, beguil'd</l>
            <l>By ſome ſmoth wanton way. But in th'end finding</l>
            <l>The path turn'd, crooked, indirect, and winding:</l>
            <l>Fals vnto running; runnes and giues not ore,</l>
            <l>And running's further then it was before,</l>
            <l>From thither it was ſent. This, like his part</l>
            <l>That towards the Sunnes decline in a deſart</l>
            <l>Is loſt, and catch'd by night: and e're't be day</l>
            <l>Is wearied ſo, and ſo farre out the way:</l>
            <l>He liues ſtrange t'a returne. Sayes, the Sunne ſhall</l>
            <l>Set, and then riſe. And riſe before he fall.</l>
            <l>All's hope's in cuſtome. Still the careleſſe ſonne</l>
            <l>To doe his owne; his father's errand's vndone.</l>
            <l>The Time's on crutches, and to ſhew wee fals</l>
            <l>Preſents vs daily with ſad funerals.</l>
            <l>Ne're more was to reform's; the time, the King</l>
            <l>Betters, and were it not that he did bring</l>
            <l>Great ſafety on's. I could not finde to ſay</l>
            <l>Encomions to time. Our King's, our ſtay,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:10"/>
            <l>Whoſe actions we may imitate; ſecure.</l>
            <l>Hee ventures nothing that to win's ſo ſure;</l>
            <l>Safty, as he that ſecond. Euer reſt</l>
            <l>This Land, this King, Queen, Prince and Councel beſt.</l>
            <l>Theſe giue the time all glory. And theſe giue</l>
            <l>Beſt fame to time; that to beſt time, ſhall liue.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 6. <hi>TO <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>IF now ſo worth, as in the ages paſt</l>
            <l>Why now not ſo much honour'd? is the taſte</l>
            <l>Of them (be fits) retaine thee: ſo decai'd</l>
            <l>They not conceiue thy full? how was betrai'd</l>
            <l>Thy firſt all-ruling courſe? Cannot the time</l>
            <l>Retaine thy good perfection? Is the clime</l>
            <l>By ignorance bereau'd? I know it's not:</l>
            <l>Th'art knowingly exil'd, moſt haue forgot</l>
            <l>Thy cuſtome, with their will, Yet is thy reſt</l>
            <l>Aſſur'd with him, and them that can the beſt</l>
            <l>Manage thy forme. And but to them eſtrang'd</l>
            <l>That from the vulgar elements, are chang'd</l>
            <l>To reele in fortunes ſphere: Such that eſteemes</l>
            <l>Not man for what hee is. But what hee ſeemes</l>
            <l>To bee. To theſe degrees I do exempt</l>
            <l>My Muſe from ſpeaking their, &amp;c. Contempt</l>
            <l>Shall after times attend the ſort: and death</l>
            <l>Shall ſpend all memory of them, After breath</l>
            <l>Concludes the funerall Sermon, not a tongue</l>
            <l>Deliuer ſhall their names. Except among</l>
            <l>The infamous to ranke them. If man ſo</l>
            <l>Intreates his fame may after ages kno</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:10"/>
            <l>As truth allowes. What more is vertues friend</l>
            <l>Then Poeſie, if will the Muſes tend</l>
            <l>Cleerely, to what they ſhould? Ciuillity</l>
            <l>Is now diſproper cenſur'd in th'agility</l>
            <l>Shee can at beſt performe. And ruder notes</l>
            <l>Fils, times infection: breathed from the throtes</l>
            <l>Of impudence. To ſerue no vertue, theſe</l>
            <l>Not, ſelfe-applauding pens; the worthleſſe pleaſe</l>
            <l>With others worthy labours: and apply</l>
            <l>A part vnto their Patrons; plac'd awry</l>
            <l>Directer aimes approue. And gather'd thence</l>
            <l>Where as the ground is free (as innocence,)</l>
            <l>From any ſeruice, from them. Theſe haue nought</l>
            <l>But borrow'd ends to offer. Nothing bought.</l>
            <l>But Baſtard ill-made iſſues. And theſe do</l>
            <l>So cloud the truer borne, makes vertue go</l>
            <l>Attir'd, not like her ſelfe. Did not the times</l>
            <l>Giue ignorant worthleſſe patrons, to theſe crimes,</l>
            <l>It would bee as it ſhould bee. Yet the times</l>
            <l>Hath wonne a maiſter that neglects theſe crimes,</l>
            <l>And's a repairing vertue. And I hope</l>
            <l>To ſee her limites haue ſo large a ſcope,</l>
            <l>As whilome, euer. 'Tis our turne to bring</l>
            <l>Now, if ere Britaines fame. Times-poets-king</l>
            <l>Accords to the deſigne. And wee haue leaue</l>
            <l>His vertues, paſſ'd. Exceeding; now to heaue.</l>
            <l>Them properly, our ſtore may take in hand.</l>
            <l>But ſtay. Another part t'our faireſt land.</l>
            <l>Mount-ſeated Atlas reares him vp to ſee</l>
            <l>His traded skye-courſe; all is arts agree</l>
            <l>Our clime the happi'ſt: ſeeing it ſo cleere,</l>
            <l>(Baniſh'd by females) would inhabite heere.</l>
            <l>For theſe be gratefull, artfull. True proclaime,</l>
            <l>Now vertues aid: can perfect vertues aime.</l>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:11"/>
            <head>ENCOM. 7. To the right Honourable <hi>Robert, Earle of Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>HIm this attends that may to mee giue grace,</l>
            <l>Though I not him. Thy truely honour'd place</l>
            <l>So worthily's reſpected. 'Mongſt which all</l>
            <l>My zeale; profeſſion look'd for: though ſo ſmall</l>
            <l>A part be put to publiſh't: This attends</l>
            <l>T'attend thy Lordly name. My Art extends</l>
            <l>Not to that high commiſſion, as can giue</l>
            <l>More fame then that which doth already liue</l>
            <l>Thy names attendant, and not more apt vſe</l>
            <l>Thy ſtare needs from the ſeruice of a Muſe</l>
            <l>Then he that's ſelfe ſupporter. Yet for that</l>
            <l>Paſt worthies, in paſt times, haue reuerenc'd what</l>
            <l>A Muſe free-borne prefer'd. To thy true worth</l>
            <l>My Muſe in her owne coulours, ſendeth forth</l>
            <l>A part proclaimes thee Lord on't. The time can</l>
            <l>Show, better lines attends a worſer man:</l>
            <l>But therefore his Muſe tax'd him; did agree,</l>
            <l>To tye her courſe to ſeruile flattery:</l>
            <l>So, wrong produc'd to both. I am too ſhort</l>
            <l>Of what thy merite claimes; and more report</l>
            <l>Reports, then I haue ſaid. Did but thy acts</l>
            <l>Beare outward ſignes like ſome. I could contract</l>
            <l>(That not the beſt do do) to thy deſert</l>
            <l>A columne; greater much, yet true a part</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:11"/>
            <l>As this, that all confirme. Thy vertues are;</l>
            <l>To many, ſtrange; and pretious as th'are rare</l>
            <l>So worth, their merite paid may duly ranke</l>
            <l>Thee in the Spheare of worth. Nor needs thou thanke</l>
            <l>Fortune: th'art not her Subiect. I reioyce</l>
            <l>Our vertuous King will make ſo truely choice</l>
            <l>Of vertue, and aduance her. Theſe times bee</l>
            <l>Stuff'd full with ſonnes ſprung from Nobilitie</l>
            <l>But they be ſonnes ecly ſ'd. I'ue vnd rſtood</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Some ſonnes are worthleſſe that had f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thers good.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Men giue not vertues, where they giue their bloud.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Th'art by bloud, worthy; and by vertues ſo</l>
            <l>'Tis euident, an vnderſtanding foe</l>
            <l>Speakes not againſt thy ſtate. The enuious ſum</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Knowing not diſpraiſe, will to praiſe be dum.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Iudgment commends thy courſe: Thy courſe not needs</l>
            <l>Of worthier ornaments. If of thy deeds</l>
            <l>My Muſe b'alow'd to ſing; and can haue place</l>
            <l>Of lik'd acceptance, in thy able grace:</l>
            <l>No welcome's more deſir'd. And my next frame,</l>
            <l>Better ſhall ſpeake thy worth; then this thy name.</l>
            <signed>Your vertues true obſeruer. <hi>AVG. TAYLOR.</hi>
            </signed>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 8. To the right Honourable, WILLIAM <hi>Lord Mounteagle, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>IReuerence more; the more I vnderſtand</l>
            <l>The cuſtomes thou obſeru'd. Vnto the land</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:12"/>
            <l>Thriuing I ſee thy ſtate, to do all right</l>
            <l>Such power could ere acquire. Not by the ſight</l>
            <l>Of feaſting eyes thy nobleneſſe can bee</l>
            <l>Truely diſtinguiſh'd. For I could not ſee</l>
            <l>When firſt I ſaw thee, any gorgeous ſigne</l>
            <l>Like them, ſome great men vſe to make them ſhine</l>
            <l>In ſhow, where ſubſtance is the moſt vnſound.</l>
            <l>Yet at firſt ſight I did perceiue the ground.</l>
            <l>Of good conſiſt in thee; with all that can</l>
            <l>Know what aduanceth and becomes a man</l>
            <l>The beſt. Will grant it thine. I ſee in thee</l>
            <l>The beſt forme of (rich-ſtor'd) humility</l>
            <l>Poſſeſſe a comely ſcope. When ſuch a part</l>
            <l>I ſaw thee, patronize: Thy great deſert</l>
            <l>I cenſur'd as 'tis prou'd. And being ſo</l>
            <l>As King and Country loues, I do beſto</l>
            <l>This embleme truely thine: Nor drawne for feare,</l>
            <l>But onely loue, and merite. It is cleare</l>
            <l>(And I'm but laſt that ſpyd't) thy countries friend</l>
            <l>Thy Country will confeſſe. Should I commend</l>
            <l>The good that all approue? admit the reſt</l>
            <l>(I'le ſpeake againſt my ſelfe) thoſe loue thee beſt</l>
            <l>That wants an Art to publiſh. This I do</l>
            <l>For that th'art truely lou'd, and my loue to</l>
            <l>Make euident as theirs. Thy name, thy ſtate,</l>
            <l>In meeteſt order well doth celebrate.</l>
            <l>But heere too ſhort my Muſe thy worth hath ſaid:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>I doubt, of great-things, I haue ſmall-things made.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Aug. Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:12"/>
            <head>ENCOM. 9. To the Truly-Honourable and right worthy, Sir THOMAS GER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RARD of Brinn, Knight Barronet, <hi>one of his Maieſties Honourable Priuy Chamber, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>I Cannot leaue to write vnleſſe thou leaue</l>
            <l>To bee what now thou art. Nor death bereaue</l>
            <l>Can thee from out my verſe. Onely a change</l>
            <l>From thy beſt worthy forme, but makes mee ſtrange;</l>
            <l>The graue not ſhall. My labours on thy name</l>
            <l>Shall long attend, as Engliſh can feed fame.</l>
            <l>Though yong my Muſe; yet not for that for thus:</l>
            <l>Suffice ſhee <hi>peior</hi> claimes, <hi>ſed peſſimus</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I know her merite paſſ'd. How ere I know</l>
            <l>This gift's, to him that can, and will beſtow</l>
            <l>Mee right. And from the time if bee my fate</l>
            <l>To gaine a ſober gray I ſhall thy ſtate</l>
            <l>Leaue in directer coulours. Th' art ſo true</l>
            <l>By birth and action worthy: to thy veiw</l>
            <l>My better part I ſend. My Muſe had wing</l>
            <l>From thy protection: and a voice to ſing</l>
            <l>From out thy bounty. Shall I tell thee what?</l>
            <l>I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot giue thee this, but onely that</l>
            <l>I know thee worthy more. In ſpeaking thee</l>
            <l>This part conferres not all that ought to bee.</l>
            <l>The times, what thou haſt beene, I can approue</l>
            <l>Can witneſſe: 'twas, thy action, wonne the loue</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:13"/>
            <l>And grace of late <hi>Eliza.</hi> All her Court</l>
            <l>Not yeelded, to maintaine a Princely ſport,</l>
            <l>A worthier Gentlemen. Admit it ſo</l>
            <l>Thy age were vndeſeruing; I do kno</l>
            <l>Thou are the worthieſt of the beſt eſteeme:</l>
            <l>If not for that thou art, for that th'has beene.</l>
            <l>Thou art for paſt admir'd; for preſent lou'd:</l>
            <l>And with the beſt reſpects. In thee hath mou'd</l>
            <l>Delight, and wiſedome. This reward doth fall;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Th'art lou'd of God, King, State, Land, mee; and all.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 10. To the Lord Arundell of <hi>Wardor, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>I, ſaid; to giue a Lord my loue; to one</l>
            <l>That nearely knew him; he ſaid euer none</l>
            <l>So form'd, his Lord accepts; and did aduiſe</l>
            <l>Mee to be ſilent. I to him replyes</l>
            <l>(Seeming my friend) to ſuch a worthleſſe Lord</l>
            <l>Were I's director hee ſhould not accord</l>
            <l>To do him ſeruice; and I told him, I</l>
            <l>Wiſht not to know his Lord, neither would ty</l>
            <l>(To write) my Muſe to flattery. For my part</l>
            <l>I deeme him worthleſſe that eſteemes not Art</l>
            <l>Cloth'd in this ancient veſt: ſo that it bee</l>
            <l>Paſſ'd the rude common ſtraines ſociety.</l>
            <l>To thee, as not of them that to a Muſe</l>
            <l>Free-borne giues no reſpect; I know to vſe</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:13"/>
            <l>Both word and ſword thou can, and art ſo farre</l>
            <l>From Poeſie's neglect, as th'art from warre</l>
            <l>Diſpraiſing. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> Muſes 'greed vnto,</l>
            <l>And did himſelfe the part they could not do:</l>
            <l>Becauſe vnknowers too't. Thou that tooke pleaſure</l>
            <l>To forme a March; daigne now to ree de a Meaſure.</l>
            <l>More, had my Muſe to ſend, and onely to</l>
            <l>Thy true renowne; then I do here beſto:</l>
            <l>This grac'd, more's bound t'attend. To one more fit,</l>
            <l>Then to the maiſter both of warre, and wit;</l>
            <l>I do not ſeeke to flye to. Thou being ſo,</l>
            <l>All vertues worthy patron; I do owne</l>
            <l>Thee truly what I giue. If ſome do ſay</l>
            <l>I giue a booke to thee, thee th'other day</l>
            <l>I did not know by ſight. More famous then</l>
            <l>Thou needs art prou'd: From knowing fame, I when</l>
            <l>Haue all confirm'd I giue; and but this comes</l>
            <l>T'vnite part of thy praiſe; that ſo the ſummes</l>
            <l>Vngather'd, plaines imperfect. This, thee to</l>
            <l>Concurres, that worthily can ſay, and do.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Auguſtine Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 11. To the Renowned Knight, Sir FRANCIS BACON his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Atturney Generall, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>ARts ſtrong ſupporter, ſhould I faile to bring</l>
            <l>My Swan to ſhore, and brought a ſhore; her wing</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:14"/>
            <l>Not perfectly aduanc'd, I ſhall repent</l>
            <l>I, tooke a taske too great. Too inſolent</l>
            <l>Ile grant my ſelfe t'haue beene. I much do care</l>
            <l>To place thy worth; which, may with beſt compare.</l>
            <l>Bounties great Patron, nor extends that part</l>
            <l>Of generous nature; but where true deſart</l>
            <l>Hath done; or's hop'd to do: Thou vnto thoſe</l>
            <l>Art bounties patron; not that daily growes</l>
            <l>To giue thy lap their actions. But to ſuch</l>
            <l>As of good ſeruice giues the ſmalleſt much</l>
            <l>To King or Country. Th'art a worthy friend</l>
            <l>To King and Country. Who will ſtriue to bend</l>
            <l>His power with all his ſtrength, when hee to whom</l>
            <l>His action, gathers forme lies farre, ot's gon</l>
            <l>From th'actor dilligent? and not any ſtayes</l>
            <l>To giue the doer, nor reward, nor praiſe?</l>
            <l>Who could forſakes to do; when no reſpect</l>
            <l>Sees merite kept vntomb'd. Thou art the man</l>
            <l>Aſſignes deſerts, rewards: Such worth, that wan</l>
            <l>The longeſt Fame, From time; what grac'd more true</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> then his granting due</l>
            <l>To merite? I amongſt, them wits ſo ripe</l>
            <l>That 'bout thee lodge, preſents a witneſſ'd type</l>
            <l>Of thy true being, who can cenſure right</l>
            <l>Thy worth, and how too ſhort this all I write</l>
            <l>Stands of thy beſt. I wiſh that all, the all</l>
            <l>I giue, be truely cenſur'd: as this ſhall.</l>
            <l>Retaine my loue how ere attir'd it goes</l>
            <l>A worthier Knight I know him not, that knowes.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:14"/>
            <head>ENCOM. 12. To the right Worſhipfull <hi>Alexander Preſſcott,</hi> Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Honourable Citty <hi>of LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>BEſt of thy place, belou'd: by mee admir'd:</l>
            <l>Why ſo, I ſhall diuulge: thy State's acquir'd</l>
            <l>So worthily; as ſhall exalt thy fame</l>
            <l>To merites height; and there ſtand with thy name</l>
            <l>An vnknowne times-progreſſion. Not as theirs</l>
            <l>Thy worth's obtain'd, that houer in the ſpheres</l>
            <l>Of greatneſſe: and for no deſert's made great,</l>
            <l>But ſeruile flattery; or reſuming ſhapes,</l>
            <l>Ridiculous obſeruations: Knaues, turne apes.</l>
            <l>Singularly attain'd to where now ſet</l>
            <l>By vertue not by fate; thou art indebt</l>
            <l>To thee, for thy aduancement: elſe to none</l>
            <l>But vnto him that merite ſets in throne.</l>
            <l>And being as thou art ſo well becomes</l>
            <l>Thy actions, thy authority; as theſe ſomes</l>
            <l>I ably can produce: Th'art lou'd for loue;</l>
            <l>Reuerenc'd for iuſtice; vertue's ſet aboue</l>
            <l>Thy will; and thou allowes't. Ne're whilome was</l>
            <l>Thy ſphere ſo grac'd, but honour'd. Now doth paſſe</l>
            <l>Rewards to like deſerts: and now preſents</l>
            <l>My Muſe her loue. Though her vnskill exempts</l>
            <l>From publicke veiw ſome parts that ſhoud attend</l>
            <l>Conioin'd; with theſe on thee: yet do befriend</l>
            <l>My Muſe, with thy acceptance; if nor I</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:15"/>
            <l>Nor ſhee can gaine't: yet may thy country try</l>
            <l>Thy natiue loue to hers; much then to her</l>
            <l>Who will not grant thou grants. I do conferre</l>
            <l>Thee rank'd with beſt deſerts. Though my courſe rare.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Clear'ſt Starres ſerue Cinthia; when the night's fayr'ſt faire.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. TAYLOR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 13. To the worthy Gentleman M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THOMAS STANDISH, (ſonne and Heire to the right Worſhipfull ALEXANDER STANDISH of <hi>Dux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, Eſquire</hi>) <hi>of Graies-Inne.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>ONce can my toyling Muſe, conteſt to know</l>
            <l>Vertues, in tender yeares. So true a ſhow</l>
            <l>Of all that hopes expect, (I note) begin</l>
            <l>In thee ground deriuation: I had bin</l>
            <l>Ingratefull to my wombe, if not to thee</l>
            <l>I had confer'd my loue: Nor loue from mee</l>
            <l>Attends, but where true merite's. Thou art borne</l>
            <l>The beſt as generous; and of ſtore t'adorne</l>
            <l>Thy ſelfe in times quaint habits: and ſo do,</l>
            <l>And when ſo done, more ſtore belongs vnto</l>
            <l>Thee innly, then thy outward 'tyring can</l>
            <l>Expreſſe. Th'art a true-worthy Gentleman.</l>
            <l>Patron of Arts. In other tongues, and lands;</l>
            <l>Speaker, and knower: them that vnderſtands,</l>
            <l>My (this-peece) Patron: Nothing doth accrew</l>
            <l>To thee in this; but vnderneath thy due</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:15"/>
            <l>A Swan keepes neere thy Spring: nor that delayes</l>
            <l>My loue to take a forme. Although his rayes</l>
            <l>Fayrer then mine: yet this hence axiom growes;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Varietas delectat.</hi> So thou knowes.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>THE AVTHOVR.</head>
            <l>PArdon, how ere theſe rank'd: for w'haue this ſway;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>A Herauld cannot, what a Poet may.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>An argument? approu'd, trie by our names;</l>
            <l>Th'on's tytles Seruant, and the other fames.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="part">
            <head>ENCOM. 14. <hi>TO POESY.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>O! that but at the rate, thou ſhould be bought,</l>
            <l>Priz'd by the true-iudicious! Time hath brought</l>
            <l>Such ſtore to bounties lap, as now's the name</l>
            <l>Of bounty turn'd illiberall, and her frame,</l>
            <l>That while-ere ſpread ſo large each hee that could</l>
            <l>Conferre; had it retain'd: did it but hold</l>
            <l>What did confirme a Muſe. What ſhould produce</l>
            <l>The alteration? Will no more the ſluce</l>
            <l>Giue the Swan leaue to prune, but in the ſtreame</l>
            <l>Deſpect her ſad confuſion? Whoſe's ſo meane</l>
            <l>In what to worth belongs, would not apply</l>
            <l>A life (if in his power) before ſhe dye,</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:16"/>
            <l>On her that ſings? ill tutord's not that hee</l>
            <l>In's education, that to harmonee</l>
            <l>Lends no affecting-eare? none was; but o!</l>
            <l>Paſt times were good; theſe times not being ſo</l>
            <l>Muſt needs bee ill. But (ſurely) ſome cauſe brings</l>
            <l>This mirthleſſe deſolation. With twelue ſtrings</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Apollo</hi> gaue's a Lute, and did preferre;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Thoſe would make Muſicke, but aboue would erre.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Since then hee left's, ſince then ſome do betray</l>
            <l>His prou'd-decree trying how more will ſay:</l>
            <l>To what's ſaid then al's ſtrangers. Th'vntrue voice</l>
            <l>Retaines more Patrons, more will (if anoice</l>
            <l>They can make) patronize. And it is now</l>
            <l>So with Diuiner Poeſie; Theſe times, how</l>
            <l>Thoſe ſing that care not: and too, in theſe times</l>
            <l>Not ſence, but words compoſeth moſt their times</l>
            <l>Now Poetizing. In this rude age-latter</l>
            <l>More ſtands to make the Meeter, then the Matter</l>
            <l>Rightly to tell. Th'authours (ſtrange) 'gree vnto</l>
            <l>Of three parts; one to ſay, and two to do;</l>
            <l>But what? iudicious cenſure! times rude rape</l>
            <l>Growing from rudeſt, lets the rudeſt ſcape</l>
            <l>Yet, their due caſtigations: doth infect</l>
            <l>Breath of coeleſtiall aire; and harſh neglect</l>
            <l>Procures to them beſtowes't; from generous ſpirits</l>
            <l>(Such throng preſents the Patrons) beſt who merites</l>
            <l>Is ſcarce diſtinguiſh'd; theſe being the crimes</l>
            <l>Of theſe right-worthy, yet vnworthy times:</l>
            <l>To grace thee and thy Muſe; them, heere ſurueies</l>
            <l>The forme I hold, that haue the perfect keies</l>
            <l>Of vnderſtandings entrance; and can giue</l>
            <l>Right to the all I giue. I did not ſtriue</l>
            <l>In this to build a frame, that might containe</l>
            <l>Large-place i'th' ſellars-ſtall; I did but aime</l>
            <l>At freedome for my next, which as my hope</l>
            <l>In formes, ſhall bee my ſhare. Me-thinkes much ſcope</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:22667:16"/>
            <l>Theſe labours did poſſeſſe; no Muſes firſt</l>
            <l>Workes ſhould bee tedious, becauſe (euer) worſt.</l>
            <l>I know thy power retaines the ancient powers</l>
            <l>It euer could: But it is thought the howres</l>
            <l>Haue numbred neere their date, and that the time</l>
            <l>Spares not our fame a time. ô 'tis the prime</l>
            <l>Our hopes affect beſt motions: ciuillizes</l>
            <l>Who er'e rightly attempts; and ſimpathzies</l>
            <l>The forme of faireſt times. Yet more belongs</l>
            <l>To do our clime more right; t'impaire theſe throngs,</l>
            <l>And out of all, giue beſt power to proceed</l>
            <l>Diuinely more, then th'ages paſt agree</l>
            <l>To celebrate. Men worth in ruder times</l>
            <l>Aſpir'd their titles; not theſe worthy climes</l>
            <l>Shall memoriz'd bee? Tha'are the trueſt faire</l>
            <l>Of paſt, and preſent, Knowing-Arts declare</l>
            <l>Our happineſſe; beſt Poeſie, Brittaine, friend;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Actions bee worthi'ſt, that doe worthi'ſt end.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Time a chiefe part conferres, this, thee I ſend:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>That may bee, Brittaines worthies (and my) friend.</hi>
            </l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
